riu.com 2017-06-06

# 

At RIU Hotels & Resorts your privacy and personal data are important to us and we will make every effort, in accordance with the legislation in place, to guarantee your protection and ability to exercise your rights.

The following conditions are applicable for RIU Hotels & Resorts services, including those offered on this website and on all of RIU Hotels' sites and mobile applications, as well as for those services offered at our hotels. In order to exercise your rights in the case of hotels managed indirectly, you must contact them directly; however, if you do not receive an appropriate response we will provide our help to resolve any differences of opinion, as long as those hotels have a working relationship with RIU Hotels & Resorts.

RIU Hotels & Resorts, as a brand which includes different companies, has centralised the management of the various aspects related to privacy and the protection of personal data with a single entity responsible for data control. The company in charge of data control is:

RIU Hotels & Resorts   
C/ Llaud s/n (RIU Centre)   
07610 Palma de Mallorca - SPAIN   
Privacy and Security Dept.

If after reading these conditions you have any doubts regarding them or the privacy of your personal data, please send an email to privacy@riu.com or a letter to the address above.

The purpose of the privacy@riu.com e-mail address is to address privacy and data protection matters. Please refrain from sending emails regarding business matters,reservations or human resources.This policy may be updated according to regulatory and legislative modifications in the various countries in which we provide our services, as well as with a view to improving our service.

 **PERSONAL DATA PROTECTION**

In accordance with the provisions of the laws in the countries in which we operate, we would like to inform users of this website, as well as any people who have provided personal information to any company associated with the RIU Hotels & Resorts brand, or to other services which we offer directly or indirectly, that this personal data is processed for the purposes of providing the services you have selected. Under no circumstances will your data be passed on to other companies for any other purpose without you being duly informed. The data you provide to us will be included in various files and appropriately registered in countries where this is a requirement.

 **A.-** The purpose of the collection and processing of the personal data supplied by users via this website, at our hotels, or through our central services or indirectly associated third parties in order to fulfill our obligations, is available, in updated written form, in our internal information security policy and in the files registered with the Spanish Data Protection Agency.

 **B.- Data collected**

In most cases, this will correspond to identification details: first name, last name, address, telephone number, email address, data for processing payments or other specific information depending on the file and purpose.

 **C.- Security measures**

RIU Hotels & Resorts is pleased to inform its customers that it has adopted the required technical and organisational measures set forth in the regulatory framework which guarantee the security of personal data and prevent its unauthorised modification, loss, processing or access, taking into account the condition of the technology, nature of the data stored and the risks to which they are exposed. All of this is in accordance with the minimum provisions set forth in the various legislations of the countries in which RIU Hotels & Resorts has a presence.

 **D.- Consent of the user**

for the processing and transfer of personal data By providing their details to RIU Hotels & Resorts or to any company associated to RIU Hotels & Resorts, the users indicate their express acceptance of these conditions and regulations of use, granting unequivocal consent for the processing of their personal data according to the purposes set forth herein. They also accept that their data may be transferred to relevant entities for fulfilment of the obligations pursuant to the service requested, exclusively for the reserved purposes, and guaranteeing they will not under any other circumstances be transferred to third parties for any other purpose, without the additional consent of the owner. By legal obligation and to ensure collaboration with the Authorities, the data may be provided to public bodies which require it. In these cases, it is specified that the minimum information required will be provided for the corresponding legal compliance, protecting the rest of the data with the utmost rigour.

When you use our online booking process in riu.com details of any hotel that you seek to reserve and your email address may be collected as you fill in the reservation process. If you do not complete your purchase, we may contact you using these details to offer our assistance (in case, for instance, you were suffering from technical difficulties). In the event that we contact you to offer you our assistance to complete your reservation process, you may exercise your rights to revocation of consent.

 **E.- Exceptions to the authorisation for data processing**

To meet our obligations to you, as well as those legally provided for, it is not required to have your express consent in the transfer of data, however this website offers you information on all aspects which may affect you, and your ability to exercise your rights.

 **F.- Right to access, correction, opposition, cancellation and withdrawal of the consent granted for data use**

The owner may exercise their rights to access, correction, cancellation and opposition, as well as withdraw their registration for the services of RIU Hotels & Resorts and the establishments it manages directly. In addition, users may, at any time, withdraw the consent they have granted for the processing of their data, without the right to apply retroactive withdrawal.   

Rights may be exercised by standard post:   
RIU Hotels & Resorts   
C/ Llaud s/n (RIU Centre)   
07610 Palma de Mallorca - SPAIN   
Privacy and Security Dept. 

Or by email to the address privacy@riu.com 

**G.- Relating to employment and specific to CVs.**

By completing an employment request, sending or submitting a CV to any company related to RIU Hotels & Resorts, the candidate does so to the companies of the RIU Hotels & Resorts group in the country in question, as well as to the head office of RIU Hotels & Resorts, through the company RIU Hotels & Resorts for the purposes of candidate assessment. RIU Hotels & Resorts complies with the applicable legal regulations on data protection and puts in place security measures and procedures for this purpose, taking into account the condition of the technology. This is in accordance with the provisions of the laws of the various countries. According to the provisions, candidates are informed that the personal data provided, including CV information, will be included in a file registered with the Spanish Agency for Data Protection, the owner of which is RIU Hotels & Resorts. Any data provided or submitted is collected by RIU Hotels & Resorts for the purposes of managing its selection database. Each owner gives their acceptance and authorisation for the processing of the personal data provided to our HR selection database, as well as the unequivocal processing or transfer of information for the purposes explicitly stated to all companies of the RIU Hotels & Resorts group. The owner of the same may withdraw the consent granted at any time, without the right to apply retroactive withdrawal. RIU Hotels & Resorts informs owners that they may exercise their rights to access, correction, cancellation and opposition, by notification in writing to the RIU Hotels & Resorts personal data controller.

 **H.- Relating to bookings or subscriptions made on the website**

In bookings for services made on this website, any personal data provided will become part of RIU Hotels & Resorts and of the marketing company for the hotel, details of which will appear on the voucher, proforma invoice or bill attached (if the booking is not made or confirmed, data will not be retained except that required for strict security purposes, to ensure successful operation of the electronic business).

 **I.- Subscription to newsletters, news bulletins or similar on our website**

The processing of personal data, as well as the sending of commercial notifications carried out via electronic means, is done in compliance with those Laws related to e-commerce and the Internet, and follows international standards and good practice, based on the general regulations of European privacy directives. Our notifications to promote and advertise our hotels and services must always provide an address by which it is possible to unsubscribe from the service that has provided the information, via a link to a website or the email address that sent the notification, and the user's email address will be unsubscribed; if any problem arises, we would be grateful if you could contact us at privacy@riu.com . In the case of subscription to newsletters, news bulletins or similar on our website, your data will become part of RIU Hotels & Resorts In accordance with the regulations in place, the information may be transferred to national or international third party companies directly related to the provision of the service for which we have been hired, as well as to local or international data controllers which comply with European Union directives.

 **J.- Information on minors**

RIU Hotels & Resorts will not try to obtain information directly from minors, although we are not always able to determine the age of those who access our website. In any case, when this is detected on both the website and in our establishments, authorisation from the parents or legal guardians of the same will be required.

 **COOKIES**

 **A.-** **Cookies and Identification of communications devices**

RIU Hotels & Resorts websites use cookies. These are small, encrypted text files that are stored on the computer or other device (smartphone, tablet, smartTV, etc.) used to access the site. Cookies remain on your hard disk or storage system and can be used by your browser at any time. You can configure your browser to accept or refuse cookies.

Accessing or using the website implies that you accept the cookies sent by Riu Hotels & Resorts and third party advertisers. You will find here the tools needed to configure your browser.

 **A.1 Types of cookies used by Riu Hotels & Resorts.**

We use different types of cookies on our website. Some are strictly necessary because they enable us to provide some of our web services and guarantee security (for example, this technology allows you to make a booking on our site). We also use functionality and performance cookies. These allow us to tailor our site to your needs and to improve our performance to maximise your experience of the site.

We use cookies for the following:

  * Online booking.
  * Site usability and functionality (to remember your preferences and the pages you have browsed)
  * To gather statistics using anonymous information.
  * To improve our performance (by identifying how long it takes for the information to reach you, etc.
  * To identify individual users that have signed up for a campaign in order give them the services included in the offer.
  * To save the browsing habits of regular site users in order to facilitate browsing and other aspects of our services.
  * Our cookies never contain personal information.

Cookies| Life Time| Type|   
  
---|---|---|---  
__sonar   
__utma   
__utmb   
__utmc   
__utmt   
__utmc_elisa   
__utmz   
_ab_proceso_reserva_chosen_cohort   
_ab_RWD_HOME_HEADER_FOOTER   
__dc_gtm_UA-XXXX   
_msuuid_2204l7214850_XXXX   
mobile   
s_cc   
s_sq   
JSSESIONID   
fp_cookieWarningSeen   
| 2 years   
2 years   
1 day   
session   
1 day   
1 day   
6 months   
1 month   
1 month   
1 day   
1 day   
1 day   
Session   
Session   
Session   
2 years   
| Performance   
Analytics   
Analytics   
Analytics   
Analytics   
Analytics   
Analytics   
AB testing   
AB testing   
Analytics   
Performance   
Traffic type   
Analytics   
Analytics   
ID session   
Msg cookies   
|   

**A.2 Manage your cookies.**

You can view, remove or manage cookies stored on your computer or communication device and also block cookies sent by Riu or its partners, or by any other website. You can configure your browser to only accept cookies from the site you are visiting, or to block cookies from third party advertisers.

These links will explain how to configure your browser:

Please bear in mind that blocking certain cookies could affect the quality of your experience on our site.

You can also visit www.allaboutcookies.org or www.aboutcookies.org. These sites clearly explain how cookies work and how you can manage them on your particular communication device and browser.

You can manage advertising cookies on websites such as www.youronlinechoices.com, which enables you to set your general preferences regarding cookies from leading Internet advertisers.

 **A.3. Third parties embedded content on our pages .**

Riu uses content such as photos and videos from websites such as YouTube and Flickr, and these sites may require cookies. In these cases, we cannot control how these are sent. Please go to the privacy and cookies policies of these third party websites to read more about their cookies and how to manage them.

 **B.- Web Beacons & Pixel Tags**

We and our data processors may use Web Beacons and Pixel Tags in emails and HTML pages. These systems do not gather personal information other than that provided by you when you make a booking on the RIU Hotels & Resorts site.

These mechanisms show us whether you have read a particular email or webpage, and allow us to track and gather statistics on the information accessed. Web Beacons and Pixel Tags will not work if you set your browser or email application to block cookies.

 **C. - Other information gathered.**

In order to make our emails to you more pleasant to read and more secure, we gather certain information, such as:

Information about your IP address, language preferences, browser and other data related to your Internet connection or connection method/application, whether you can receive information in HTML format, and any other non-personal information supplied by the application you use to connect to the Internet.

Please note that we will register information concerning Internet or email connections in order to troubleshoot any problems that may arise, improve our performance and services, and manage security issues.

January 2017
